Guide to the New England Society in the City of New York Records 1805-1941 MS 3113
New-York Historical Society
New England Society in the City of New York records
1805-1941 (Bulk 1889-1937)
New-York Historical Society
New England Society in the City of New York
MS 3113
29.5 Linear feet in 28 boxes (25 record cartons and 3 oversize cartons).
The collection consists of records of the New England Society, a social and charitable organization whose membership consisted of New Yorkers from New England. It documents approximately 140 years of the Society's internal governance, membership files, financial administration, social events, and charity work for poor New Englanders in New York.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into six series that reflect the work and documents of the New England Society:
Series I. Governance, 1805-1941
Series II. General Correspondence, 1854-1913
Series III. Membership Records, 1850-1925
Series IV. Charity Records, 1829-1925
Series V. Financial Records, 1824-1937
Series VI. Event Records, 1870-1922
Researchers should note there is some overlap in subject matter between some of the series, primarily between the various series and General Correspondence, which includes administrative, financial, membership, and event matters.
Each volume in the collection was given a unique identifier (e.g., SN-1, SN-2) by the processing archivist. These are intended only to facilitate reference and are not indicative of any overall numbering scheme found in the collection itself.
Biographical / Historical
The New England Society in the City of New York (the "New England Society") was founded in 1805 as a social and charitable organization, whose objective was to promote the "friendship, charity, and mutual assistance" between those from and the descendants of New Englanders in New York City. At the first meeting, the Society's seventy members elected James Watson, both a former New York Senator and the meeting's host, to become its first President. The organization was formally incorporated in 1833.
To become a member of the New England Society, a candidate had to apply and be elected into the membership. By 1920, membership had swelled to over 1,200, although this number varied year to year due to deaths, resignations, and new elections. Until 1872, women were not present at Society receptions, dinners, or events. Prominent members of the Society include painter John Trumbull, financier J.P. Morgan, Mayor of New York City Seth Low, Supreme Court Justice Charles Evans Hughes, members of the Tiffany family, and U.S. Secretary of State Elihu Root. Some, such as Morgan, Low, and Root, also served as President of the New England Society or held other officer roles. Famous New Englanders, such as presidents John F. Kennedy and Calvin Coolidge, feature among the Society's honorary members.
Starting in 1806, the New England Society formed its Charity Committee, which oversaw the use of some of the society's funds for charitable purposes. Beginning in 1817, the Society provided annuities to support downtrodden New Yorkers who either came from or whose families came from New England, including widows, orphans, and elderly men, among others. The treasurer's records and financial documents demonstrate the continuation of this practice of charity well into the twentieth century, as the Society also liaised with other New York charitable organizations to identify and to disburse funds to those in need of assistance.
The Society celebrated its proclaimed New England values by hosting an annual celebration at some of New York City's upscale hotels. Starting in December 1805, the Society hosted its Annual Dinner (also known as the Annual Festival) at the City Hotel to commemorate the anniversary of the Pilgrims landing on Plymouth Rock. The dinners, which were also hosted at noted New York locations like Delmonico's and the Waldorf-Astoria Hotel, invited many esteemed figures from American society, including the President of the United States, cabinet secretaries, senators, financiers, and industrialists. While many of these figures declined their invitations, some, such as presidents Woodrow Wilson and Theodore Roosevelt, attended these dinners. These dinners often included addresses and speeches explaining the history of New England or praising its contributions to American society.
The New England Society also sought to commemorate the historical contributions of New Englanders to American history through memorials and celebrations. In 1885, the Society donated the Pilgrim Statue, sculpted by John Quincy Adams Ward, to New York City, which now stands at E. 72nd Street in Central Park. In 1920, the Society also supported the Pilgrim Hall Museum in Plymouth, MA, by donating $50,000 for the creation of a fireproof portico to protect the nation's oldest public museum and fundraising to support the preservation of documents from Plymouth Church in Provincetown, MA. The Society had contracted the famous architecture firm McKim, Mead, and White to design the Pilgrim Hall's Portico.
The New England Society continues to operate today under the leadership of President Ellen Scordato, committing itself to promoting New England history, culture, and values in New York City. Since 1953, the Society has offered a scholarship to New York City students attending colleges in New England. Additionally, the Society's Book Award and Reginald T. Townsend Award–-both awarded at the Annual Dinner–-seek to honor publications and individuals who embody New England culture and values.
(The above note was based on materials in the collection and the website of the New England Society in the City of New York, as well as the Wikipedia page for the New England Society.)
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the New England Society in the City of New York, 1942
Scope and Contents
The New England Society in the City of New York records include documents produced by the organization between 1805 and 1941, primarily focused on its internal governance, financial administration, and various social events.
Governance: The series contains 12 volumes and loose records relating to the internal administration of the New England Society. This includes the volumes of meeting minutes that run from 1805 until 1941, volumes of supporting documents for those meetings, a committee book, as well as loose records of election ballots for Society officers, miscellaneous meeting minutes, and administrative documents. The series paints a picture of both the everyday administration of the Society, but also the way in which its officer board and directors were selected by the members of the Society.
General Correspondence: The series contains 9 volumes and loose correspondence. This includes the letterbooks of outgoing mail from the secretary, as well as a file of all incoming and outgoing mail of the Society. Organized chronologically, the topics cover most aspects of the Society's functions, including internal communication between officers, membership inquiries, Annual Dinner planning, communications with charitable organizations and cultural institutions, and announcements to members. For more granular details, please consult the "Scope Notes" of individual folders.
Membership Records: The series contains 5 volumes and loose materials relating to the Society's membership, including member rolls, a scrapbook of newspaper clippings, applications, and assorted correspondence. Most correspondence pertains to membership recommendations, death notifications, deaths, and internal correspondence about membership elections.
Charity Records: The series contains mostly loose material relating to the Society's charity work, including multiple committee reports, documents about specific charity cases, applications for annuities, and correspondence with charitable organizations about their services for individuals.
Financial Records: The series contains 19 volumes and loose records relating to the financial administration of the society. Records in this series include account books; dues collection books; vouchers and voucher books; bank statements and cancelled checks; investment records; Finance Committee and treasurer reports; and the treasurer's memos, which largely correspond with personal papers and correspondence about the financial administration of the Society.
Event Records: This series contains documents relating to events hosted and/or sponsored by the Society. The Annual Dinner and Festival subseries includes guestbooks, correspondence, programs, stenographer reports, and printing plates for invitations and menus from the Annual Dinner. Of particular note are some of the invited guests, which included the likes of Woodrow Wilson, Theodore Roosevelt, and J.P. Morgan. Additionally, the series includes lectures, sermons, yearbooks, dedications, book printings, and the records of other dinners and socials. Another item that would be of interest to researchers is the Pilgrim Hall Portico documents, which include the spec report created by the architectural firm McKim, Mead, and White for the design of the project.
Charities -- New York (State) -- New York.; Clubs -- New York (State) -- New York.; Dinners and dining.; Societies -- New York (State) -- New York.; New England.; Financial records.; Letters (correspondence); Membership lists.; Minute books.; Printing plates.; Scrapbooks.; Sermons.; Speeches (documents); Vouchers.; Morgan, J. Pierpont (John Pierpont), 1837-1913; Low, Seth, 1850-1916; McKim, Mead & White
- Series I. Governance, 1805-1941
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains 12 volumes and records most directly related to the administration of the Society. This includes the volumes of meeting minutes, supporting document books, as well as scattered copies of meeting minutes, election ballots, and other meeting material. Most of these records have been organized according to their meeting type and date, but unordered groups of administrative documents have been placed under the name of "Secretary's records." These records provide a rich image of the Society's various meetings, as well as the election of the officers and directors, which amounted to the Society's trustees.
  Arrangement
  The series is organized by document type and chronologically, with volumes being first.
  - Minutes, vol. 1, 1805-1836 (Offsite-box 22, Volume SN 29)
    In addition to the minutes for all meetings in stated time period, this volume also contains the constitution and by-laws of the New England Society.
  - Minutes, vol. 2, 1837-1856 (Offsite-box 27, Volume SN 28)
  - Minutes, vol. 3, 1857-1884 (Offsite-box 22, Volume SN 31)
  - Minutes, vol. 4, 1884-1898 (Offsite-box 22, Volume SN 34)
  - Minutes, vol. 5, 1898-1906 (Offsite-box 22, Volume SN 35)
  - Minutes, vol. 6, 1907-1915 (Offsite-box 21, Volume SN 14)
  - Minutes, vol. 7, 1915-1923 (Offsite-box 21, Volume SN 30)
  - Minutes, vol. 8, 1924-1933 (Offsite-box 21, Volume SN 33)
  - Minutes, vol. 9, 1933-1941 (Offsite-box 21, Volume SN 32)
  - Book of officers and committees, 1894-1902 (Offsite-box 24, Volume SN 24)
  - Supporting documents book, vol. 1, 1894-1899 (Offsite-box 21, Volume SN 68)
    This volume includes correspondence, committee reports, treasurer reports, and other documents discussed during a meeting of the Society.
  - Supporting documents book, vol. 2, 1899-1909 (Offsite-box 28, Volume SN 67)
  - Annual Meeting records, 1894 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 11)
  - Special Meeting records, 1894 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 10)
  - Annual Meeting election ballots, 1894-1906 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 12)
    Includes the ballots cast by members at the Annual Meeting to elect the new year's governing body of the Society; for Annual Meetings and/or Special Meetings that had their own files during this time period. Ballots found with the Special Meeting or Annual Meeting records were kept together.
  - Monthly Meeting records, 1895 January (Offsite-box 7, Folder 13)
  - Annotated by-laws, 1900 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 13)
    This document includes handwritten annotations suggesting edits to the by-laws, such as changing the requirements and language around admission into the Society and membership.
  - Special Meeting records, 1901 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14)
  - Special Meeting records, 1904 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 15)
  - Annual Meeting records, 1905 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 17)
  - Secretary's records (4 folders), 1906-1908 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 3-6)
- Series II. General Correspondence, 1854-1913
  This series contains 9 volumes and loose correspondence, most of which was addressed to and from the Secretary of the New England Society. The letterbooks consist of carbons of all outgoing mail from the Secretary to various figures, chief among them the Society's President, officers, and members. The loose correspondence includes both outgoing and incoming mail. The contents of these letters vary, covering topics such as membership inquiries; financial concerns; internal communication between officers; correspondence with cultural institutions about the history of the Pilgrims and materials from the Society; charity cases and disbursements; and the Annual Dinner, mostly concerning guests, tickets, and seating arrangements.
  This series is organized by document type and chronologically, with all volumes coming first.
  - Letterbook, 1894-1901 (Offsite-box 18, Volume SN 37)
  - Letterbook, 1901-1908 (Offsite-box 18, Volume SN 36)
  - Letterbook, 1908-1909 (Offsite-box 18, Volume SN 8)
  - Letterbook, 1909 December - 1910 September (Offsite-box 18, Volume SN 41)
  - Letterbook, 1910 September - 1911 April (Offsite-box 18, Volume SN 40)
  - Letterbook, 1911 April - November (Offsite-box 18, Volume SN 38)
  - Letterbook, 1911 November - 1912 February (Offsite-box 18, Volume SN 39)
  - Letterbook, 1912 February - October (Offsite-box 18, Volume SN 43)
  - Letterbook, 1912 October - December (Offsite-box 18, Volume SN 42)
  - "Letters from Distinguished Men", 1854-1885 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 6)
    Includes letters from notable contemporaries, such as Henry Ward Beecher, William Evarts, and William Aspinwall.
  - General correspondence, 1894 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - General correspondence, 1895-1905 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 10)
  - General correspondence, 1897-1901 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - General correspondence, 1898-1902 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 1)
    Includes correspondence with Edward Towne about the history of the Pilgrims and the purpose of history within the Society.
  - General correspondence, 1902 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - General correspondence, 1903 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes a directory of charities from the United Charities organization.
  - General correspondence, 1904 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - General correspondence, 1905-1906 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes an invitation from the New-York Historical Society inviting members of the New England Society to see an exhibit of a series of miniatures, which had been donated to the N-YHS from the NES, as well as two affividavits and correspondence regarding McLaurin J. Pickering and the 1906 Annual Election of the NES.
  - General correspondence, 1907-1908 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - General correspondence, 1909 January - February (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - General correspondence, 1909 March (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes correspondence about the production of centennial medals for the Society, as well as a proposal addressed to then-President Seth Low for the creation of a Society clubhouse.
  - General correspondence, 1909 April - May (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - General correspondence, 1909 June - September (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - General correspondence, 1909 October - November (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - General correspondence, 1909 December (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - General correspondence, 1910 January (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - General correspondence, 1910 February (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    Includes a letter from H.A. Cushing to Seth Low about low attendance of board members.
  - General correspondence, 1910 March - April (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    Includes correspondence about a "free bed" endowed at the Presbyterian Hospital for $5,000 in 1893.
  - General correspondence, 1910 May - June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    Includes an invitation for the Society to participate in the New York Fourth of July parade.
  - General correspondence, 1910 July - September (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
    Includes correpondence about the selection of a speaker for the annual dinner later in the year, including names like Woodrow Wilson, then President of Princeton, as well as George B. McLean, former Governor of Connecticut. Other topics of note include correspondence regarding the Pilgrim Memorial Monument in Provincetown, MA.
  - General correspondence, 1910 October (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - General correspondence, 1910 October - November (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - General correspondence, 1910 November (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
  - General correspondence (2 folders), 1910 December (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - General correspondence, 1911 January - February (Offsite-box 23, Folder 11)
    Includes correspondence about new events for the Society, such as a garden party, in addition to the annual dinners, as well as correspondence with the North Carolina Society about the Weeks law then facing a vote in the Senate.
  - General correspondence, 1911 March (Offsite-box 23, Folder 12)
  - General correspondence, 1911 April - June (Offsite-box 23, Folder 13)
  - General correspondence, 1911 July - December (Offsite-box 23, Folder 14)
  - General correspondence, 1911-1912 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
    Includes correspondence and promotional material for a lecture before the Society by George H. Tripp
  - General correspondence, 1912 January - June (Offsite-box 23, Folder 15)
    Includes letter to members of the Society exhorting them to recruit younger, eligible members, with an application attached to the letter.
  - General correspondence, 1912 July - December (Offsite-box 23, Folder 16)
    Includes correspondence about the funeral of journalist, writer, and NES member Whitelaw Reid (1837-1912), as the President of the Society appointed multiple members to be representatives at his funeral.
  - General correspondence, 1912-1913 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
- Series III. Membership Records, 1850-1925
  The series consist of 5 volumes and loose material relating to the Society's membership, including member rolls, applications, and assorted correspondence. The applications allow a researcher to understand the requirements to gain admission to the Society, as well as trace their evolution over a period of 30 years. The assorted correspondence mostly covers inquiries from members about dues, the recommendation of potential members to the Society, resignations, and notifications of deaths.
  The series is organized by document type and chronologically, with all volumes coming first.
  - Members book, 1850s (Offsite-box 24, Volume SN 21)
  - Member rolls, 1895 (Offsite-box 26, Volume SN 25)
  - Member rolls, 1905-1914 (Offsite-box 26, Volume SN 26)
  - Member rolls, 1915-1925 (Offsite-box 26, Volume SN 27)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings, 1894-1905 (Offsite-box 28, Volume SN 69)
    Clippings cover the mentions of New England Society members in the news, mostly their obituaries in papers like the New York Times and New York Herald Tribune.
  - Applications (17 folders), 1894-1912 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-17)
  - Applications (7 folders), 1913-1921 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-7)
  - Applications (4 folders), 1922-1925 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 23-26)
  - R.W. Meade ancestry letter, 1894 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 9)
    Letter to trace the lineage of R.W. Meade for the purposes of membership in the New England Society.
  - Reported deaths of members, 1896-1903 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9)
  - Resignations, 1899-1908 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 8)
  - Membership correspondence, 1909-1910 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 1)
  - Membership correspondence, 1911 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 2)
  - Membership documents and lists, 1911-1912 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 3)
    Includes copies of applications, notices to members about life membership, and list of alphabetized names, likely candidates nominated elected to the Society's membership between 1909-1912.
  - Membership correspondence, 1912 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 4)
  - Membership correspondence, 1913 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 5)
- Series IV. Charity Records, 1829-1925
  The subseries contains 1 volume and mostly loose documents relating directly to charity, including correspondence, committee reports, case descriptions, and applications for annuities, which the Society would give to those who demonstrated need for assistance.
  This series is organized chronologically.
  - Charity Committee report, 1829 (Offsite-box 15, Volume SN 16)
  - Charity applications, 1888-1893 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 8)
  - Charity correspondence, 1894-1896 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 6)
  - Charity correspondence, 1897 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 7)
    Includes the initial endowment of the free bed in Presbyterian Hospital for $5,000.
  - Charity correspondence, 1908-1909 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 8)
  - Charity correspondence, 1910-1911 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29)
    Includes two charity committee reports, from March and December 1910.
  - Francis D. Stead and F.B. Miller charity cases, 1911-1912 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 4)
  - Charity correspondence, 1912 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 3)
  - Mrs. W.P. Robeson, J.F. Hackett, and Charles Small charity cases, 1912-1913 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 5)
  - Charity Committee reports, 1913 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 8)
  - Mary Everdell and Mrs. Willard Frazier charity cases, 1913-1914 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 7)
  - Harriet Brooks and Mrs. T.H. Wood charity cases, 1913-1914 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 6)
  - Charity Committee reports, 1913, 1919, 1925 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 10)
- Series V. Financial Records, 1824-1937
  The series contains 19 volumes and loose documents relating to the financial administration of the New England Society. Documents included in this series include cash books; account books; vouchers and voucher books, which tracked the expenses of the Society; dues collection books; bank statements and cancelled checks; investments and letters of advice; Finance Committee and Treasurer's reports; and the treasurer's personal papers and correspondence, called "Memos" for the purpose of this series.
  This series is organized alphabetically by document type and chronologically.
  - Account book, 1833-1834 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 1)
  - Account book, 1845 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 1)
  - Account book, 1888-1889 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 2)
  - Account books, 1904-1906 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 3)
  - Account book, 1914-1917 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 21)
  - Account book, 1929 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 4)
  - Account book, 1929 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 28)
  - Balance sheets and checks, 1900-1904 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 10)
  - Balance sheets and checks, 1906-1907 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 14)
  - Balance sheets, 1909-1911 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 16)
    Includes associated correspondence.
  - Bank statements and checks, 1924-1926 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 11)
  - Bank statements, 1929-1930 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 29)
  - Bank statements, 1930 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 16)
  - Bank statements and checks, 1936-1938 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 14)
  - Bank statements and checks (5 folders), 1927-1935 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 8-12)
  - Cash book, 1884-1893 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 7)
  - Cash book, 1899-1905 (Offsite-box 19, Volume SN 7)
  - Cash book, 1903-1922 (Offsite-box 20, Volume SN 9)
  - Checkbook, 1924-1928 (Offsite-box 20, Volume SN 3)